<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="contestant">
    <title>Contestant manual</title>
    <section id="contestant.intro">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
            <firstterm>Abacus</firstterm> is a software package for programming
            contests. You will use it to submit your solutions and get
            feedback from the judges.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="contestant.starting">
        <title>Starting Abacus</title>
        <para>
            The command to start <application>Abacus</application> will depend on your local
            installation. In most cases you should just be able to type
            <userinput>abacus</userinput> in a terminal window.
        </para>
        <para>
            After starting <application>Abacus</application>, you should select
            <menuchoice><guimenu>Abacus</guimenu><guimenuitem>Connect</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
            This will open a dialog box. The server and port should have
            already been set for you. Fill in the username and password that
            you have been given. If you do this correctly, you should receive
            the message <computeroutput>You are now connected to the
                server.</computeroutput>
        </para>
        <para>
            When the contest is running, you will see a clock in the
            bottom-right corner counting down the remaining time.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="contestant.clarifications">
        <title>Clarifications</title>
        <para>
            If you are uncertain about some details in a task or the contest
            in general, you may submit a clarification request. On the
            <guilabel>Clarification requests</guilabel> tab, click
            <guibutton>Request Clarification</guibutton>. Select the problem
            your query pertains to and type in your query.
        </para>
        <para>
            When a judge responds to your query, the response will
            be available on the
            <guilabel>Clarifications</guilabel> tab<phrase
            id='contestant.view-clarification'> (you can double-click on
            clarification requests and clarifications to see the full
            text)</phrase>.
        </para>
        <para>
            Some things to take note of:
        </para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The newest information appears at the top.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    In a distributed (multi-site) contest, the judges might
                    not be on-site. Thus, if you have specific questions about
                    the installation at your site (e.g., your IDE won't open)
                    then speak to somebody at the site.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The judges do not know who is submitting queries. This
                    means that if you want to refer to a previous query you
                    made, you should include the <guilabel>Request
                        ID</guilabel> that appears in
                    the list box. Similarly, if your query is about a
                    particular submission, you should include the
                    <guilabel>Submission ID</guilabel> from the Submissions
                    tab (or use the <guibutton>Request
                        Clarification</guibutton> button on that tab &mdash; see
                    <xref linkend="contestant.submitting"/>).
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    You may receive clarifications for questions that you
                    never asked.  These are broadcast replies and indicate
                    important information for all contestants.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="contestant.solutions">
        <title>Writing your solution</title>
        <para>
            If you are using Java, you can call your main class whatever you
            like, but it must be the <emphasis>first</emphasis> class in the
            file. You can include support classes after it, but they should
            not be <symbol>public</symbol>.
        </para>
        <para>
            Your solution will read from standard input
            (<code language="c">stdin</code>,
            <code language="c++">cin</code>,
            <code language="java">System.in</code> or
            <code language="python">sys.stdin</code>, depending on language)
            and write to standard output
            (<code language="c">stdout</code>,
            <code language="c++">cout</code>,
            <code language="java">System.out</code> or
            <code language="python">sys.stdout</code>).
            Your solution is tested by an automated marker, so you must be
            careful to input only what is asked for, and output only what is
            asked for. In particular, do not print prompts or messages like
            <computeroutput>The answer is:</computeroutput> unless you are
            asked to.
        </para>
        <section id="contestant.solutions.float">
            <title>Floating-point output</title>
            <para>
                In some questions, you may be asked to give output that is
                correct to a particular number of decimal places. It is
                recommended that you use the following code fragments to
                produce correct output for such questions (in all the cases
                below, we assume that the number of decimal places asked for
                is 6, and that the variable <varname>x</varname> is the value
                to be output).
            </para>
            <example id="contestant.solutions.float.python">
                <title>Floating-point output in Python</title>
                <programlisting language="python"><![CDATA[print "Case #%d: %.6f" % (caseNum, x)]]></programlisting>
            </example>
            <example id="contestant.solutions.float.java">
                <title>Floating-point output in Java</title>
                <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[System.out.println(String.format(
    "Case #%d: %.6f", caseNum, x));]]></programlisting>
            </example>
            <example id="contestant.solutions.float.cxx.stdio">
                <title>Floating-point output in C++ with stdio</title>
                <programlisting language="c++"><![CDATA[printf("Case #%d: %.6f\n", caseNum, x);]]></programlisting>
            </example>
            <example id="contestant.solutions.float.cxx.iostream">
                <title>Floating-point output in C++ with iostreams</title>
                <programlisting language="c++"><![CDATA[cout.precision(6);
cout << "Case #" << caseNum << ": " << fixed << x << endl;]]></programlisting>
            </example>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section id="contestant.submitting">
        <title>Submitting your solution</title>
        <para>
            When you are ready to submit a solution, go to the
            <guilabel>Submissions</guilabel> tab and click <guibutton>Make
                Submission</guibutton>. Be very careful to select the right
            problem, source file and language in the dialog box, as there are
            penalties for incorrect submissions and there is no way to reverse
            an accidentally submitted solution.
        </para>
        <para>
            Once you make a submission, it will appear in the list box, with
            newest submissions at the top. The status field will let you keep
            track of the submission status. The possible options are:
        </para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><computeroutput>Pending</computeroutput></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The submission is still in the automatic marker.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><computeroutput>Compilation failure</computeroutput></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Your submission did not compile. This can happen with
                        C++ in particular, because the marker might not be
                        using the same version of the compiler. To assist you,
                        <phrase id='contestant.comp-output'>you can double-click
                        on the submission</phrase> to get the compiler output.
                        In many cases you just need to add a
                        <code>#include</code> statement. There is no time
                        penalty for compilation failures. Note that since
                        Python is an interpreted language, there are no
                        compilation errors &mdash; so be particularly careful
                        before submitting, as what would be a compilation error
                        in another language will be a run-time error in Python
                        and will cost you penalty time.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><computeroutput>Time limit exceeded</computeroutput></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Your program exceeded the maximum time limit. This
                        could mean that it is too slow or has an infinite
                        loop.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><computeroutput>Abnormal termination</computeroutput></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Your program has crashed for some reason. Possible
                        reasons include using too much memory, writing an
                        excessive amount of output, throwing an uncaught
                        exception, using illegal memory in C++, and returning a
                        non-zero exit code (in particular, your
                        <function>main</function> function in C++ must return
                        0).
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><computeroutput>Deferred to judge</computeroutput></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The program produced an output file that was judged
                        wrong by the automatic marker. A judge will look at it,
                        and if the only error is in formatting it may be judged
                        correct. You should not rely on this.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><computeroutput>Format error</computeroutput></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        A judge has looked at your output and noticed that your
                        solution does not conform to the output format in the
                        problem statement.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><computeroutput>Wrong answer</computeroutput></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        A judge has confirmed that the answer is wrong.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term><computeroutput>Correct answer</computeroutput></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Well done!
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para>
            Judges report the first condition they notice. In particular,
            <computeroutput>Format error</computeroutput> does not indicate
            whether the answers are correct or not, and <computeroutput>Wrong
                answer</computeroutput> does not indicate whether the format
            is correct or not.
        </para>
        <para>
            If you wish to ask a question about a particular submission, you
            should submit a clarification request and mention the
            <guilabel>Submission ID</guilabel> in your request. A quick way to
            do this is <phrase id='contestant.sub-clar'>to use the <guibutton>Request
                Clarification</guibutton> button on the
            <guilabel>Submissions</guilabel> tab &mdash; if you have selected a
            submission from the list box, then clicking on this button</phrase> will
            open a clarification request window with the correct problem
            selected, and the <guilabel>Submission ID</guilabel> entered in the
            request text.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="contestant.standings">
        <title>Standings</title>
        <para>
            You can see the standings at any time (from the
            <guilabel>Standings</guilabel> tab), but they will not be updated
            during the last hour of the contest. Only teams that have made at
            least one submission will appear in the standings.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="contestant.alerts">
        <title>Alerts</title>
        <para>
            When a hidden tab has new information (such as a reply to a
            clarification, or the result of a submission), <phrase
            id='contestant.flag'>the flag next to</phrase> the
            tab title will light up red.  Click on the tab to see the update.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
