<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="licensing">
    <title>Licensing</title>
    <section id="licensing.abacuscm">
        <title>AbacusCM</title>
        <para>
            This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
            modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
            as published by the Free Software Foundation; version 2
            of the License.
        </para>
        <para>
            This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
            but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
            MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
            GNU General Public License for more details.
        </para>
        <para>
            You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
            along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
            Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA
            02110-1301, USA.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="licensing.jquery-ui">
        <title>jQuery UI</title>
        <para>
            This software contains portions of <ulink
                url="http://jqueryui.com/">jQuery UI</ulink>, which is
            distributed under the following terms (MIT license):
        </para>
        <para>
            This software consists of voluntary contributions made by many
            individuals (AUTHORS.txt, <ulink
                url="http://jqueryui.com/about"/>) For exact
            contribution history, see the revision history and logs, available
            at <ulink url="http://jquery-ui.googlecode.com/svn/"/>
        </para>
        <para>
            Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person
            obtaining a copy of this software and associated documentation
            files (the "Software"), to deal in the Software without
            restriction, including without limitation the rights to use, copy,
            modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies
            of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is
            furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:
        </para>
        <para>
            The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be
            included in all copies or substantial portions of the Software.
        </para>
        <para>
            THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND,
            EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF
            MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND
            NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT
            HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY,
            WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM,
            OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
            DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="licensing.jquery">
        <title>jQuery</title>
        <para>
            The AbacusCM source distribution includes components of
            <ulink url="http://www.jquery.org/">jQuery</ulink>, which is
            distributed under the MIT license above.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="licensing.cometd-javascript">
        <title>cometd</title>
        <para>
            This software contains Javascript code from <ulink
                url="http://www.cometd.org/">cometd</ulink>, which is licensed
            under both the <ulink
                url="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/apache2.0">Apache
                2.0</ulink> and the <ulink
                url="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/mit-license.php">MIT
                license</ulink>.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="licensing.docbook-xml">
        <title>DocBook XSL Stylesheets</title>
        <para>
            The documentation for this software includes images that form part
            of the <ulink
                url="http://docbook.sourceforge.net/release/xsl/current/doc/">Docbook
                XSL stylesheets</ulink>, which is distributed under the
            following terms:
        </para>
        <para>
            Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person
            obtaining a copy of this software and associated documentation
            files (the <quote>Software</quote>), to deal in the Software without
            restriction, including without limitation the rights to use, copy,
            modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies
            of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is
            furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:
        </para>
        <para>
            The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be
            included in all copies or substantial portions of the Software.
        </para>
        <para>
            Except as contained in this notice, the names of individuals
            credited with contribution to this software shall not be used in
            advertising or otherwise to promote the sale, use or other
            dealings in this Software without prior written authorization from
            the individuals in question.
        </para>
        <para>
            Any stylesheet derived from this Software that is publically
            distributed will be identified with a different name and the
            version strings in any derived Software will be changed so that no
            possibility of confusion between the derived package and this
            Software will exist.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>File uploader</title>
        <para>
            This software contains portions of <ulink
                url="http://github.com/valums/file-uploader">File
                Uploader</ulink>, which is distributed under the GNU General
            Public License, version 2 or later.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Icons</title>
        <para>
            The connection status icons (<filename>connected.png</filename>
            and <filename>disconnected.png</filename>) were downloaded from
            <ulink
                url="http://www.easyvectors.com/browse/other/9f6520f14dc7b7a7eb25a85f01628d39-button-green-clip-art">here</ulink>
            and <ulink
                url="http://www.easyvectors.com/browse/other/button-red-clip-art">here</ulink>,
            and are free for commercial use.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
